Okay, so now let's
look at our first
tool that we can
use in the emotion
brick. And it works
like this. So let's
say you're planning a
video and you've got
five mistakes that you
want to point out
and you're planning point
one. You're probably thinking,
well, how do I
create emotion there? And
the first question I
always ask myself at
this point to enable
me to do this
is quite simply, how
can I show the
problem or the transformation
or proof this works?
And that is it.
And the first tool
for the job that
I think of first
before anything else is
called a visual demo.
So a visual demo
is when you in
the emotion brick either
show the problem, show
a contrast of a
before and after, or
you break down the
problem. So in this
video, what I'm going
to do is I'm
going to show you
how to use each
of these. And I'm
going to give you
a decision matrix to
help you work out
when you should or
should not use them
in your videos. Okay,
so let's start with
our first type of
visual demo. I call
showing the problem in
the emotion brick. Okay,
so one of the
most simple ways to
create an emotional reaction
is to visually show
the problem your viewer
is facing in a
way that makes them
go, ah, I finally
get it because I
can see it. If
you do that, you
have hooked them and
you're going to warm
up fast. Now, the
reason this is so
powerful is because 99
% of people on
YouTube are just going
to sit there and
describe a problem to
a viewer. And the
viewer then has to
use their brain to
try and picture it.
And often they can't
because it's just information,
not visual. But also
people's descriptions are often
so badly put together,
viewers get lost, bored
or confused. But when
we show the problem,
we do a ton
of the work for
them and their brain
connects the dots instantly
and it feels new,
easy and inspiring to
them. So let me
show you an example
of this in action,
as you have already
experienced me showing you
the problem multiple times
in this program. So
think back to this
visual demo I showed
you with the gold
and red YouTube. If
I had said to
you, your first 10
videos will probably fail.
Maybe the 15th will
be okay. 20 to
25 might get better,
but the 29th could
maybe flop again. That
is just too hard
to follow. There's so
many numbers and your
brain's doing mental gymnastics,
trying to picture all
of that. So nothing
sinks in. But when
I laid it out
visually like that, and
I just said the
gold is a video
that performed above average
and will grow your
channel and the red
does not. So over
time, just repeat what
works and you'll get
more yes. And then
the yellows, that should
have clicked instantly because
you can literally see
the problem. So that's
what showing the problem
does. It stops your
viewers brains having to
strain to keep up.
So it feels easy.
And then it gives
them the crystal clear
realization that feels new
and inspiring. And that
creates the emotional reaction
we need to keep
them listening so that
they then want to
go on to the
logic brick. So let
me give you a
few examples of how
this might work too.
So let's say you
run a weight loss
channel. And you diagnose
the problem your viewers
have and the point
you want to make
solves. That is soda
is one of the
main reasons you're not
losing weight. So you
could just say that
and it's not very
effective. Or you show
the problem by stacking
16 sugar cubes on
top of each other
and asking, would you
lose weight if you
consumed this much sugar
a day? Probably not
right? But that's how
much is in just
one can of Coke.
So when you combine
that with a human's
average sugar intake, you
get 26 sugar cubes.
So if you're still
drinking this stuff, cut
it out and watch
the pounds fall off.
So that's emotional because
it's going to shock
the viewer. It's visual.
So it's easy to
understand as they don't
have to decode anything.
And it's inspiring because
it's easy to cut
out one can of
Coke a day to
lose weight. So we
hit on the three
key things needed to
convert viewers to buyers.
But who should use
visual demos? Well, it's
perfect for creators teaching
strategy, business or mindset.
Anyone explaining why something
isn't working. Videos where
the problem is solved.
Where the problem is
invisible or very abstract.
Lessons where your viewer
needs a wake up
moment before they listen.
Or if you're ever
thinking they won't get
this unless I show
them why it matters.
This is your go
-to. But there's a
big mistake you have
to avoid when you're
doing this. So imagine
that I'd made my
YouTube expectations chart look
like this. And I
said the blue ones
are videos that perform
10 % above average.
The gold 20%. The
red average. The purple
10 % below average.
And the black 20
% below average. It
doesn't work does it?
Because the art is
distilling this down to
only the core parts.
Not filling in every
minute detail. So the
mistake is making your
visual demos far too
complex. They have to
be simple. Now, when
do you use this?
Well, when you are
planning you just got
to ask yourself. Will
the viewer struggle to
picture the problem? Would
a single image, visual
or clip make it
obvious? Or would a
two second demo deliver
more than two minutes
of explanation? If the
answer is yes. We
use a visual demo.
Now, you're not just
going to magically go.
Oh, I know how
to show the problem.
This is easy. So
here's a little process
you can go through
to help you find
ideas. So the first
thing you want to
do when you think
you want to show
the problem is ask.
What's the problem my
viewers have? And then
you ask. Can my
viewers see the problem?
And if the answer
is no. You then
ask yourself. Well, how
could I show them
the problem in a
very simple way so
they can see the
issue rather than have
it up there? And
that's why the sugar
cubes works and the
diagram works. That's it.
Okay, so that is
showing the problem as
a visual demo. Now
let's look at the
second type of visual
demo, which creates a
very strong emotional reaction
I call contrast demos.
So this is where
you show your viewer
a clear before and
after or a wrong
versus right or a
low impact versus high
impact image, chart or
video side by side.
So here's an example
of this in action.
What we need to
do is see if
we can salvage this
by saying. What's the
reason your channel exists?
So for example, I'm
going to say. So
the reason they want
to learn to color
grade, they want to
make really slick content
that like levels up
people's personal brands. So
the first thing I
look at with this
headline is could we
position it as something
like, and again, it's
not that in line
with your channel, but
something like stick out
faster on social media
with HBO quality video.
And then maybe instead
of your color grading
box, which most people
won't understand because it's
quite an advanced thing.
You replace that with
a before and after
shot. Like don't show
this weird dashboard. No
one cares about that.
What we want is
people to land and
instantly go, Oh, that's
what I want. And
then to see a
visual that goes, that's
how I want to
look so that they
then read the sub
headline that's below. Now
this is incredibly powerful
because our brains are
wired to spot patterns
and pattern spotting is
how we learn. So
the moment they see
the difference, a lesson
clicks. Now, another example
might be, let's say
you're teaching people how
to solve the problem
of an awful LinkedIn
profile. So you show
the before then the
after. So the viewers
are hooked by the
difference. They can clearly
see, and then you
go on to explain
how to get that
result in the logic
brick, but who should
use a contrast demo?
Well, if you make
content that shows a
transformation reviews, rows, so
before and after results,
this is perfect. And
it's incredibly powerful when
the contrast creates this
kind of like yikes
or aha moment where
the viewers sit in
there thinking I've been
doing version a, but
I want to be
version B. But when
that happens, you've really
hooked him. Okay. So
when should you use
a contrast? Am I?
Well, if you're teaching
people. A transformation, so
old versus new strategy.
If you want someone
to ditch a habit,
a mindset or a
tool, if you want
them to realize they're
doing something wrong so
that they can actually
see how to fix
it. If you want
to inspire action by
showing the outcome they
could have. So it's
kind of similar to
the first one, but
slightly different. Okay. So
now let's look at
the mistakes you got
to avoid here. And
it's very similar to
before because you need
to avoid causing overwhelm
and confusion
by adding in too
much complexity at this
point. So. If you're
pointing out three contrasts
or three problems in
your before and afters,
just point out three
max. And then in
your visuals, you need
to make sure that
they're not cluttered. So
let's say you have
a screenshot like this
and you only want
to talk about this
area here. You need
to use an arrow
to point to the
exact thing you're talking
about. Don't just assume
that the viewers are
going to lock on
just because you know
exactly where in the
image is the problem.
We've got to make
this easy. But what's
the best option for
you to use? Well.
Okay. So. Like before,
there's some questions you
can ask yourself here
to work out. So
I would ask, would
a before and after
image clearly show the
improvement? Would a wrong
versus right split screen
make the lesson obvious?
Could a side by
side image remove doubt
or hesitation better than
an explanation? And if
the answer is yes,
you use a contrast
demo. If not, just
skip that. Don't force
these in at all.
It's the same for
all of them. And
then you can move
on to the third
option we have for
visual demos, which is
called a breakdown. So
a breakdown is when
you pause, slow down
or comment on something
like a video clip,
an image, a document
or a web page
to teach people what
the person or the
thing in it is
doing. You're basically saying,
let me just freeze
this right here and
show you exactly what's
going on. So here's
an example of that
in action. Most people
we interact with have
boring conversation habits. So
being around someone who
makes us laugh and
feel good is almost
like a drug. We
want to be around
that person all the
time. One way Craig
does this is with
a high energy, enthusiastic
compliment. You look sensational.
I mean, sensational. Well,
thank you. Look at
that. You look at
you, woman. You look
sensational. Now, this works
because it makes the
invisible visible and it
helps your viewers understand
how something works or
why it works without
overwhelming them again. They
also reduce overwhelm and
focus attention. And they
give your viewer the
feeling of mastery. Like
they now understand the
thing they didn't before.
If you do that,
that's an incredibly motivational,
emotional response, which is
going to pull them
towards your logic brick
and make everything feel
new, easy and inspiring.
Okay. So let's look
at another example.
So let's say you're
helping someone figure out
why their Airbnb isn't
performing. You pause the
screen on a real
Airbnb listing and you
say, let's freeze this
right here. This is
a top performer because
of three things. Firstly,
because the first photo
is showing the best
room in the house,
which hooks someone the
second it loads and
it's going to blow
up their clicks. And
then the title says
two minutes from town.
So it gives an
immediate benefit and look
at the description. Bullet
points that only list
the things people care
about. Wifi, check in
ease and proximity. So
this is kind of
like the comparison, but
you just break down
what's working rather than
what's not. And so
who should use these?
Well, if you teach
someone something that's visually
specific, like design, marketing,
movement, interfaces, ads, funnels,
body language, you're showing
your viewer how something
works or fails in
real time. This is
a great option for
you. If you want
your viewer to replicate
what you're explaining, this
is another great option.
And if you want
your viewers to go,
oh, I've never noticed
that until you pointed
it out. Breakdowns are
going to happen. I
hope you do that.
Now, just like the
others, there's some big
mistakes you need to
avoid here. That's going
to wreck this. Firstly,
don't overload the frame.
Like I just said,
you need to use
visuals and arrows and
labels and commentary, and
then point out one
thing at a time.
And then don't assume
what's obvious to you
is obvious to them.
Also, you want to
strip away absolutely anything
visually distracting in your
demo. You can crop
images and screenshots you
take, you know, don't
get lazy with this
because it really does
make a massive difference.
Reduce the amount of
information the viewer's brain
has. And then you
can also use the
image that's in the
video to help them
understand what's happening. So,
when should you use
this? Well, ask yourself,
is there something visual
here that needs to
be slowed down or
zoomed in on? Would
freezing or pausing the
moment help clarify a
teaching point? Would showing
how it works be
more effective in describing
it? If yes, that's
a breakdown moment. Okay,
so now it's time
to bring back this.
Remember that thing from
the intro module called
a transition? So, a
quick reminder, a transition
hooks forward to the
next chunk of information
and signals movement to
the viewers so they
feel like they're progressing.
So, after your emotion
brick, we need to
use a transition to
hook forward to our
logic brick so that
viewers feel like what
they just saw now
leads directly into the
steps that they need
to take. If you
don't signal that shift,
or the transition, the
viewer's going to think,
wait, is the demo
finished? Is this a
new idea? What's going
on? And that little
moment of friction will
kill your video's power.
So, instead, we give
them a clean handoff
from emotion to logic
using a simple transition
line. And that could
be something like, so
now you've seen the
problem, here's how to
fix it. Okay, so
let me show you
the steps to get
the same result. Or
here's how to apply
this for yourself. Or,
all right, so what
can you actually do
to get this result?
Now, there's tons of
different ways of doing
it. There's a transition
link in the video.
Plan it if you
need it. But before
we get into the
next video, I'm going
to show you an
incredibly powerful tool for
building emotion. I need
to give you maybe
the most important advice
in this entire module.
So, finding ways to
use visual demos and
then transitioning into logic
is very hard. And
when you start doing
this, and they don't
just instantly come to
your mind in two
seconds, and you spend
two hours getting nowhere,
just remember that frustration
is part of your
transformation into the Hulk
you will one day
become. But, it has
taken me millions of
words of scripts and
years of practice to
finally have these things
just appear in my
brain in seconds. But
it only happened by
trusting all the science,
all the data, and
all of the results
that followed using this
to believe that the
effort would one day
pay off. So to
get good at this,
to truly master it,
guess what? We have
to fail as fast
as we can. So
just give yourself permission
to suck at this
to start. You're going
to. And you will
eventually, if you practice,
get to the point
where it starts to
feel easier without even
thinking. Alright, so there's
a little quiz below
this video. Fill it
out and see what's
sunk in. And then
move on to the
next.